some of you may not know that I have
multiple sclerosis I was diagnosed 10
years ago and just to make this very
long story short throughout those 10
years I have managed it with lifestyle
and God has really blessed me with that
and I've just the disease is there and
there sometimes they're symptoms but for
the most part God led me through a
journey step by step on how to live a
healthy life above the symptoms and you
know sometimes in our life things are
going so well and we depend on God a lot
when we are at the beginning of going
through something and then as we start
to feel a little stronger and more
confident in what we're doing sometimes
we are tempted to either not depend on
God as much or not do all that God has
told us to do I don't know am I the only
one that experiences that sometimes
well I definitely experienced that
through this journey like I said I was
diagnosed ten years ago and I've never
had a flare-up the first time that I was
sick and had symptoms was 10 years ago
and had some symptoms and that's I was
diagnosed and after we've we've been
here for five years last year was
actually our fifth year anniversary last
year sorry last Sabbath was our fifth
year anniversary so we've been here for
five years so after moving up here I
continued to do the lifestyle things
that God had showed me and it was and it
was going pretty well then about almost
two years ago based around the time that
my stepfather passed away do you guys
remember that
my stepfather passed away and that was a
very trying time for our family because
he was so amazing for my mother he was
the rock for my mother and he was such
an amazing grandfather to my children
and a stepfather to me and just just
supportive of our whole family and when
that happened I I immediately went into
I guess stress worry mode because I knew
I had to be there for my mother so I did
everything she became I just did
everything that I could for her from
afar and then seeing her as soon as I
could and it really I didn't realize it
at a time at the time but he emotionally
took and a lot from me and caused a lot
of stress that I was internalizing but I
really wasn't aware of that but during
that time stress a lot of stress
happened a lot of the lifestyle changes
that God showed me on how to live
healthy with multiple sclerosis I
stopped doing some of those things like
you know I just got busy as you know I
was in school and in my master's program
and so I was still doing like 50% of it
but not everything that I knew I needed
to do after after graduating I really
this last year this last year has been
very stressful the last ten months has
been quite stressful and you know I
thought I was handling it pretty well
you know I'm have that strong
personality I can just move forward deal
with things I can take all these things
on and not be so stressed out but my
body was not my body was taking in that
stress and so two weeks ago I had my
first multiple sclerosis flare-up and in
that process it was I mean I knew what
the numbness those are you who are
familiar I'm sure the medical
professionals here are familiar but it
starts with the numbness and tingling in
my extremities and really on my right
side is where it always begins and it
just started to to move very quickly to
the right to the left side and my legs
and my and my feet into my hands my
abdomen it was I was partially Naumann
tingling all over
and I started to I mean I knew what it
was and I said okay let me start doing
those things that I know I should be
doing and I started doing those things
and that wasn't working and I and by
after a couple of days of that I I made
a decision I gotta call my doctor
and once he assessed me he he said you
know you're gonna have to get on this on
high doses of steroid and infusion he
was like I can either put you in the
hospital or you can come you need to do
five days of these infusions or you can
come back and forth and I chose to be
able to come back and forth because at
that time I thought oh I can still work
and even though I'm not feeling well I
can do the infusions and those types of
things well it progressively got worse
after I saw him I try to get an
appointment that day for the first
infusion but the our insurance companies
god bless them drugged their feet to
approve it before and so the infusion
facility clothes before they approved my
infusion so I didn't get it done that
day so I started taking some oral
steroids and those were not touching it
at all my my my symptoms were getting
worse and that was on Sabbath that
section at the last time I was here and
that was on a Sabbath and it started to
get worse on Sunday the next day it was
worse and I said Iver you need to take
me to the ER because I can barely walk
by this time my feet I grew up in the
country so this is what I compared it to
if you run out if you go if you run
outside barefoot which we shouldn't but
I was a little kid if you run outside
barefoot and you get mud on your feet
and it dries does anyone know what that
feels like okay I grew up in the country
okay so that's what my feet felt like it
felt like I was drawing on walking on a
big stack of mud with tingling and
numbness I don't know if you can even
imagine what that feels like
and my legs were very weak so that was
causing me not to walk very well so I
went to the ER and I had my first
infusion still didn't have any relief
from those symptoms the second day third
day and I called the doctor and I said
I'm getting no
from these symptoms I mean from the
infeed the symptoms are still there and
they doing the infusions and he said he
said you need to do these infusions
because we're just trying to stop the
movement the rapid movement of the MS
through your body right now this is a
flare-up but he said I cannot guarantee
that you will get you will be able to be
the way you were before they started and
that was as you can imagine very
discouraging to me and my and my husband
and so that was on a that was that was
on a Wednesday I believe and I just
cried out to God at home I don't know if
any of you have ever done this but I
cried out to God and I was like and I
was in my room by myself the kids were
at school or and at work and I believe I
ever was in the house but he was
somewhere else in the house and I just
cried out to God and I just said Lord
you have brought me these last 10 years
through this MS and I mean literally
crying and I don't want to say yelling
but very loudly talking to God and I
just said God you've brought me through
this for 10 years and you've always been
right there with me please heal me and
help me and it was very quiet in my
house
but I felt the presence of God and I
believe that God at that time he healed
me not completely physically at that
time but he healed my heart he walked me
through all the stress that I have
carried and all the burden that I'm
allowed to be internalized inside of my
body and my mind and not surrendering
those things to him he immediately
changed me in that area I was telling my
husband prior to this happening I was
not happy about some things I was strut
definitely stressed about some things
and those things were paramount in my
mind they were the first things I
thought about the first that's what I
always taught when I was talking to him
there's the first things that I talked
about all the time and on one of our
trips to the hospital I said it's
amazing how those things are not
important when your life is being when
you're facing a life-threatening illness
that could change your life or take your
life I didn't care about those things
anymore all I cared about was getting
better all I cared about was being here
for my family all I cared about was just
God healing me and working this thing
out in my life like I didn't care like I
wasn't stressed I still prayed about
those things but I just left it at
Jesus's feet it didn't make me sad
throughout the day I didn't have those
negative emotions that I was carrying
around and God just spoke to me he just
showed me that you know I I claim that I
have faith and that I believe in him but
I take the reins and try to control
things in my life and I take the stress
of these negative things that happened
in my life and I internalize them and
they're affecting my body like I
literally me and God were talking and in
our where he showed me that for me to
not stress is like life and death
like when I stressed the inflammation of
my body goes crazy and we all we all
hear that that stress is a killer but
stress is a killer
and people can cause you stress people
can attempt have to rephrase that they
can attempt to cause you stress and pain
it's like a loaded gun right but when we
allow it to affect us that's pulling the
trigger a loaded gun doesn't kill you
pulling the trigger kills you so when we
allow stress even if there's mean people
Our Lives there's people that don't mean
well for you they don't like you your
job your children what whatever the case
is we live in a sinful world we're going
to deal with negative things but when we
allow that stress to be internalized
into or when we accept it in our minds
and allow it to be internalized into our
bodies that is when it becomes a huge
health issue for us I have to give you
an example of what God has done for me
share this but the pastor gave me this
opportunity so I may share it but there
was nothing my new motto is it's okay it
doesn't matter
God has everything under control so
every time something happens that's what
I say and it and I the reason why I'm up
here sharings cuz I was sharing this
with our family at worship last night
and I was like would you like to share
that before the church and I you know
because I made a promise it's the other
thing I made a promise to God that if he
would heal me enough to get back on my
feet and help me to feel back to the way
I was feeling prior to this attack I
will always speak and share whenever I'm
asked I won't hesitate my husband didn't
know that when he asked me but God
reminded me in the middle of the night
last night that I did make a promise and
that's why I'm up here speaking but the
example of what God has done for me and
I think this shocked my family because
they know me so well was this week iver
and I were having a discussion and the
topic was usually something that would
cause us to be at odds and and I would
be tempted and many times fail and get
into a stressful and way and be angry
and not talk so kindly about this topic
and so the topic came up and he actually
said some things that you normally would
trigger me to be very upset and he was
and he wasn't trying to trigger me but
just that's what would normally happen
and so
he said it and I felt in my body like it
was the normal thing the normal pathway
that my brain had made for so many years
to stress out and to become angry i I
couldn't it I automatically just went to
a very calm spirit and my response was
very calm and it just ended that
discussion in a negative way and we were
able to pray and move oh I'm sorry
thank you in a positive way usually it
would have ended negative but it was
able to end positive because I was able
to respond to him and in a positive way
so that is that's that's that's really a
miracle I'm just learning to trust God
with everything not letting anything
stress me out it doesn't matter what it
is I could I don't want to take up so
much time there's many examples of
things that have happened since I've
made that decision and giving that to
God and every time God just I'm just
reminded I surrender it and he even
gives me the emotions of peace and
happiness I really want to encourage you
because I'm not the only one I mean yes
I have multiple sclerosis but you may
not have a disease but stress but stress
can cause a disease and again it doesn't
matter we're all going to be in
stressful situations at times and maybe
you are in one right now and a
relationship in a marriage and they're
in your job with your children it
doesn't whatever it may be but God wants
to teach all of us which he took that
he's taking me through this for me to
learn this lesson but he wants us all to
learn how to abide in him and it's also
taught me to appreciate the very small
than smallest smallest things in life if
we just take time to give God thanks for
everything
and know that he is God and he can take
care of everything and so there's no
need to stress or worry about anything
even when you don't like it when
someone's doing something that you
disapprove of you pray and you show them
love and that's what I want to close
with just extending one way an easy way
an easier way not to stress is to and
this is something I show my client I I
talk about with my clients and therapy
is extend grace to yourself always
trying to help clients learn how to love
themselves and to extend grace to others
when clients come in to my office when
we do family of origin issues so many
times it's connected back to their
family they've been through some type of
traumatic experience and they tell me
you know some horrible thing their
parents did to them or something
horrible that something somebody did to
them and I as a therapist I
automatically go to I wonder what
traumatic thing happened to that person
when they were you in their life that
caused them to be like that to then
eventually treat other people that way
and so you teach your clients to extend
grace to yourself but to extend grace to
that person as well so when we're
dealing with each other in our church
family life or at work or at school or
whatever when somebody's not that great
to you or they're not being nice to you
or they say things that are hurtful just
think about I wonder what that person
what happened to that person that caused
them to feel that pain that causes them
to act that way and extend grace to them
that way we don't stress we don't worry
we don't we don't hold those bitter
feelings of anger and unforgiveness all
of that your body records all of that
your body keeps and it causes harm to
your physical being there's a whole lot
more to my testimony but I believe God
has I've shared enough and I just want
to encourage everyone to trust God and
to depend fully on him
so um I uh I told the tante she should
just take the whole sermon and she was
like no I'm just gonna be up there for
like five minutes and I was like good
time come on and she's like no no no and
she could have said the whole sermon but
the title of this sermon is actually
called the king of peace the king of
peace and in our scripture reading today
it was Isaiah 9:6 where Jesus is called
the Prince of Peace he is the ruler of
peace the opposite of stress is peace
and stress kills I want to invite you to
open your Bibles with me to the book of
Genesis chapter 13 Genesis chapter 13
and I'm going to abbreviate some of this
because I want to try to get straight to
the point here but in Genesis chapter 13
verses 1 through 3 we're not going to
read the whole thing but I'm going to
tell you what happens there in Genesis
chapter 13 Abraham and his nephew lot
are in this situation where their herds
men are fighting with one another and
Abraham says to lot listen the land is
too small for us so you go one way and
you choose and I'll go the other way and
I want you to just notice Genesis 13 and
if we can notice very quickly Genesis 13
verse verse 8
the Bible says here in Abrams said on
Abram said unto lot lot let there be no
strife I pray thee between me and thee
and between my herdmen
and thy herdsmen for we be brethren is
not the whole land before before thee
separate thyself I pray thee from me if
thou will take the left hand then I will
go to the right or if thou depart to the
right hand then I shall go to the left
and notice verse 10 and lot lifted up
his eyes and beheld all the plain of
Jordan that it was well watered
everywhere for the Lord destroyed Sodom
and Gomorrah even as the Garden of the
Lord even like the land I'm sorry like
the land of Egypt as thou cometh unto
xot are then lot chose him all the plain
of Jordan and lot journeyed East and
they separated themselves from one
another
Abram dwelt in the land of Canaan and
lot dwelt in the cities of the plain and
pitched his tent toward where everyone
Sodom verse 13 but the men of Sodom were
wicked and sinners before the Lord
exceedingly have you ever heard the
phrase the grass looks greener on the
other side lot looks around and he
notices what he feels is that would be
prime real estate for me that is what I
want have you ever made a decision in
your life based on how it looked to you
man this looks good this is what I want
this is ideal let me tell you sometimes
that which looks like the Garden of Eden
that which looks like ah this is the
will of God for me sometimes that can be
a path that God did not design for you
to take the Bible says there is a way
that seems right unto a man
but the end thereof are the ways of
death sometimes our eyes can deceive us
sometimes our will can deceive us
proverbs 12 verse 15 notice what it says
the way of a fool is right in his own
eyes but he that harken if unto counsel
is wise and proverbs 419 proverbs 419
the way of the wicked is as darkness
they know not at what they stumble let
me ask you which way is it better to
trust your way or God's Way God's Way
because listen your way is going to lead
you into trouble of situations your way
is going to lead you to unnecessary
stress to unnecessary heartache how many
of us have made decisions where we found
ourselves stressed out based upon the
decisions we made when we walk in our
ways we actually separate ourselves from
Christ just as as lot separated from
Abraham when we choose our ways we
separate ourselves from Christ Jesus
himself said in John 14:6 I am the Lord
the way the truth and the life and in
John 10 verse 1 Jesus said anyone who
tries to come into my house some other
way is a thief and a robber there is
only one way beloved in that way is
Jesus Christ now I want you to notice
Genesis chapter 14 because
abran la goes to dwell in Sodom and then
we find the situation unfolding in
Genesis chapter 14 I'll begin reading
verse 1 it says and it came to pass in
the days I'm going to read it from the
screen it came to pass in the days of of
am rafael king of shinar arioch king of
ellasar Colonia or king of elam and
tidal king of nations verse 2 that
made war with bera king of sodom bursa
king of gomorrah shayna king of abner
and similar or similar king of zeboiim
and the king of bela that is so are so
you may not have notices but there are
nine kings altogether four kings versus
five kings and the Bible tells us that
this battle unfolds in a place verse 3
it says all these were joined together
in the Vale of Siddim which is the salt
sea now why is this valid important to
our our message this morning because if
you jump down with me to verse 11 and 12
I want you to notice what happens here
it says then they took all the goods of
sodom and gomorrah and all their
provisions and went their way verse 12
they also took who locked abraham's
brother's son who dwelt where in sodom
and his Goods and departed so i want you
to catch what's happening here
Locke sees a place that he thinks this
is good territory this is what I want
this is where I want to dwell and he
goes to dwell near Sodom what ends up
happening is that this great battle
unfolds between these nine kings four of
them are going out to war against five
of them and two of the five kings are
the kings of Sodom and the king of
gomorrah where lot
dwell and what ends up happening but of
it is locked gets taken in this battle
let me rephrase it this way lot gets
caught up in this battle between these
kings
what kind of kings were these were they
righteous kings they were what Cana
Kings
they were worldly kings so Lots decision
leads him to get caught up in the Battle
of worldly kings I don't know if you
caught that
lot's decision to go against Horta to
step outside the will of god leads him
to get caught up in worldly conflicts
how often do our own decisions to go
against the will of God lead us to get
caught up in conflicts that are worldly
conflicts that lead to stress and lead
to anxiety and lead to all these
different issues the Bible says love not
the world neither the things that are in
the world but when we make our decision
to separate ourselves from God to go
another way what ends up happening is we
get caught up in worldly things Romans
chapter 12 verse 2 it says be not be
transformed by the renewing of your mind
be not conformed to this world but be
transformed we get caught up beloved in
earthly battles in earthly conflicts in
wars after the flesh and that is what
that is one of the most serious things
that leads to us being in stressful
situations anyone know what it's like to
be in a stressful situation anyone know
what it's like to be in that stressful
situation and wonder did I bring this
stretched stressful situation on myself
which only amplifies a stressful
situation which only amplifies your
thought of did I bring this and you see
this never-ending cycle of stress that
is designed to destroy you
it's very interesting anyone know notice
that one of these kings the four kings
was the king of shinar anyone know where
shanaar is where is it Babylon he was
the king of Babylon and I want you to
understand this church because Babylon
and I'm talking about spiritual Babylon
I'm talking about that endtime power
time Babylon who has as its King Satan
is really out to do nothing but cause
you stress
can anybody testify to that Satan's goal
is to cause you stress this battle is in
some places known as the Battle of the
nine kings that sounds like an epic
title to me the Battle of the nine Kings
Locke got caught up in this battle of
the nine kings and I'm saying that in
the same way you and I when we separate
from Christ as lot separated from
Abraham we can get caught up in this
battle of nine kings and I want to
suggest to you a symbolic picture of
these nine kings I'm gonna suggest to
you that there are nine emotional kings
that war over the soul those kings are
the kings of worry stress fear anxiety
depression bitterness Envy hate and
doubts when we step away from the will
of God and go our own way when we
separate from Christ as lot separated
from Abraham we allow ourselves to
become captive to these emotional kings
has anyone met any one of these
emotional kings that just seemed to
dominate your life and rule over you as
LA was taken captive so many of us have
been taken captive by these emotional
kings these kings that have no mercy on
the soul and that's why I like this
verse Genesis 14 and I want you to
notice with me verse 14 in fact
let's go back to verse 13 the Bible says
and there came one that had escaped and
told Abram the Hebrew for he dwelt in
the plain of Mamre the Amorite brother
of Esau and brother of Anna and these
were Confederate with Abram and when
Abram heard just stop right there you
guys should know me by now when I read
this verse when Abram heard look at me
right now guys when Abram heard
I like that guys I mean it you kind of
get this picture of when Abraham went
when Abraham here's what they have my
nephew when Abraham heard when God heard
Jana feeling me
when Abraham heard that his brother was
taken captive now let's pause for a
second his brother wait a minute who is
that who was lots of him but it calls
him his brother you know if we would
care about one another like that if we
would have that say know someone that's
yeah that's my brother one when Abraham
are heard that his brother was taken
captive he armed and that's what this is
where I just get goosebumps guys he
armed he is like no no no no no no no
I'm not leaving my brother to be to be
harassed and to be taken by these kings
the Bible says he armed his 318 trained
servants who were born in his own house
and went in pursuit as far as Dan notice
worth verse 15 in fact we're gonna pull
it off in verse 15 I want you to turn to
Psalm 18 verse
six we can get it up on the screen psalm
18 verse six Psalm 18 verse six the
Bible says in my distress let me ask you
any of you ever been in distress any of
you ever been captive to worry or fear
or doubt or anxiety or those nine kings
we talked about when you are in that
when you are being tormented by these
emotional kings look at what the Bible
says in my distress I called upon the
Lord and cried out to my god
he what he heard my voice from his
temple and my cry came before him even
to his ears and what do you think God
does when he hears your cry
what do you think he does when he hears
your suffering when he hears your plea
for help he comes Isaiah 59 notice with
me verses 16 to 19 Isaiah 59 he saw that
there was no man and Wonder that there
was no intercessor therefore his own arm
brought salvation for him and his own
righteousness it sustained him verse 17
for he put on righteousness as a
breastplate and a helmet of salvation on
his head he put on the garments of
vengeance for clothing and was clad with
zeal as a cloak verse 18 according to
their deeds according he will repay fury
to his adversaries recom for a comments
to his enemies the coastlands he will
fully repay and notice verse 19 so shall
they fear the name of the lord from the
west and his glory from the rising of
the sun when the enemy comes in like a
flood the Spirit of the Lord will lift
up a standard against him beloved listen
to me just as Abraham went after his
brother who was in captivity so Jesus
Christ came after us when we fell into
sin all mankind rebelled against God and
said we're going out
Way and we're gonna do our own thing and
they end up get we ended up getting
ourselves in trouble but God does not
say well you made your decision you made
your bed lying in it he says I'm coming
after you I will come to find you and to
redeem you this is why in Luke chapter 4
verse 16 through 19 when Jesus comes on
his mission the Bible says so he came to
Nazareth where he had been brought up
and as his custom was he went into the
synagogue on the Sabbath day and stood
up for to read verse 17 and he was
handed the book of the prophet Isaiah
and when he found the book when he had
opened the book he found the place where
it was written listen carefully the
Spirit of the Lord is upon me because he
has anointed me to preach the gospel to
the poor he has sent me to heal the
broken watch hearted and to proclaim
Liberty to who the captives just as
Abraham went out to deliver lot from his
captive state beloved Jesus Christ came
to this earth to deliver you and I from
our captivity Genesis 14 back in Genesis
14 we're going to start reading from
verse 15 Genesis 14 verse 15 the Bible
tells us this Genesis chapter 14 and
verse 15 he divided his forces against
them by night he and his servants
attacked them and pursued them as far as
homer which is north of damascus verse
16 so he brought back all the goods and
also brought back his brother lot and
his goods as one of the women and the
people let me tell you something in this
story of abraham going after lot and
bringing him back is a story of the plan
of salvation it is a story of what god
desires to do for you and i it is a
story that lets us know that God does
not design that we should be captive to
anyone captive to anything he comes
beloved as a
man-of-war he comes as a man-of-war
notice with me Psalm 24 the entire Psalm
Psalm 24 is speaking of Jesus leading
captives to the Kingdom of Heaven and I
want you to notice Psalm 24 beginning
with verse one Psalm 24 and verse one
let's see if we can get it up on the
screen Psalm 24 verse 1 the Bible says
the earth is the Lord's and all its
fullness the world and those that dwell
therein verse 2 he has founded it upon
the Seas and established it upon the
waters who may ascend into the hill of
the Lord or who may stand in his holy
place he who has clean hands and a pure
heart who has not lifted up his soul to
an idol nor sworn deceitfully verse 5 he
shall receive the blessing and other
from the Lord and righteousness from the
god of his salvation this is Jacob the
generation of those who seek Him who see
your face say 'la now I want you to
notice what it says next lift up your
heads o ye gates and be lifted up you
everlasting doors and the King of what
glory shall come in let me ask you who
is the king of glory the king of glory
is Jesus notice what it says in verse 8
who is this King of glory
the Lord strong and mighty the Lord
mighty in what mighty in what everyone
battle listen to me pause for a second
when Abraham goes out to get his brother
lot you realize he's going up against
how many kings he's going up really
against four kings because the four have
gone to war against the five but lot is
stuck in the middle of this earthly
conflict but Abraham he has 300 and
something trained servants think about
that guys 300 trained servants are going
out to fight against four
with kingdoms don't ask me how it is
that Abraham with 300 men go into enemy
territory and delivers Lots and his
family from these Kings would you say
Abraham was mighty in battle would you
say that Jesus is mightier than Abraham
in battle that Ivan listen to me Jesus
came to this earth as an army of one to
go up against all the kings of this
earth the Bible says we wrestle not
against flesh and blood but against
spiritual wickedness in high places
Jesus came as an army of one to deliver
you and me this is why the Bible says
that we must fight the good fight of
faith
because Abraham is showing us a picture
of Jesus as a man of what a man of war a
man of war now I'm going somewhere with
this because in this same story come
back with me to Genesis chapter 14 and
in the same story Genesis 14 and we're
going to look now at verse 17
Genesis chapter 14 and verse 17 because
as Abraham is coming back from this
battle the Bible says something very
interesting here Genesis 14
verse 17 it says and the king of sodom
went out to meet him at the valley of
shaveh
that is the king's valley after his
return from the defeat of kerala mark
and the kings who were with him and not
now notice verse 18 then Melchizedek how
have you ever heard of that name
Melchizedek Melchizedek king of where
Salem brought out bread and wine he was
the priest of God Most High and you know
what happens in the story he blessed him
and said blessed be Abraham of God Most
High possessor of heaven and earth verse
20 and he blessed and blessed be God
Most High who has delivered your enemies
into your hand and he gave them a tithe
of all know who is no Catholic okay some
of you said Jesus he is not Jesus he's a
type of Jesus why is he a type of Jesus
what does the named Melchizedek mean
well let me ask this way who was
Melchizedek he was king of Salem what
does the word Salem mean what does it
mean everywhere heard someone say Salam
or Shalom what is that
peace so king of Salem means king of
peace now watch these guys you have in
this story two men Abraham who serves as
a type of Christ as a man of a man of
war and then Melchizedek who is also a
type of Christ but his name means king
of well how is that how was this story
that we're reading in a Bible showing
Christ as both a man of war but also
king of peace
remember peace is the opposite of stress
how was God revealing himself as both a
man of peace or a man of war but also a
man
peace I want you to notice with me
Exodus 1414 Exodus chapter 1414 you turn
there when you get there just say Amen
are you there
everybody should be there cuz it's on
the screen I want you to check this out
guys how is it that that that the Lord
says I'm a man of war but he also
presents himself as king of peace you
see it in Exodus 14 14 the Bible says
the Lord will do what's right for you
and you what are you supposed to do what
are you supposed to do okay so if if I
give you my Bible to hold and then I say
hey guys no matter what happens don't
let any don't let go of this Bible don't
let anyone take this Bible from you what
am I telling you to do I'm telling you
to hold hold your Bible right hold my
Bible so if I'm holding it if I'm
commanded to hold something that means
do not want let it go God says listen
here's how this man of war man of peace
thing work I will do what fight for you
and your job is to do what hold your
peace
hold it so when we hold our peace we
think okay be quiet we think all right
just sit back and don't do anything no
hold your peace why because the devil is
trying to do what
take your piece and he'll use situations
he'll use people he'll use whatever he
can to take your piece and to exchange
it for distress so Jesus says listen I
have come into this world to give you
peace my peace did he say that he said
my peace I leave with you now why is he
giving us his peace because his peace is
tried and proved his peace has been
proven why because he came to this world
as the king of peace and so Satan was
like oh you're the king of peace all
right well I'm gonna do everything in my
power to what to steal your peace I'm
gonna do everything in our power to
stress you out and so now we begin to
see that as Jesus comes to this world
he's coming to this world to redeem us
he's coming at him as a man of war but
his battle weapon his battle axe is
peace and sayd now realizes if I can
steal his peace then I have him so you
know what happens we we go to Matthew
chapter 4 and we go to Matthew chapter 4
and we read in Matthew chapter 4 that
Jesus goes into the wilderness remember
that story he goes into the wilderness
and he's there for how long he's there
for 40 days and 40 nights and let me ask
you a question are the circumstances
dire in these 40 days and 40 nights are
they but does Jesus
his piece in the midst of his dire
circumstances so you know what he's
shown us he's the saint listen my piece
is a battle-tested piece that's the
piece I'm giving to you a piece that can
withstand dire circumstances around you
how many remember when Jesus was on the
ship remember when that storm came up
and and the Bible says that the
disciples were on the ship and everyone
was terrified and everyone's scared and
Jesus rises from the ship rises and he
says why are you without faith he turns
to the storm and says what he says peace
be still Jesus is telling us look my
piece is weather tested peace that means
my peace can last whether the Sun is out
or whether it's cloudy how many of you
know what it's like when you get up in
this cloudy or like today's a day for
depression because it is cloudy just
cause it's cloudy it's gonna be a bad
day Jesus says the peace I give you the
peace I give you is a piece that is
weather tested it will be consistent
whether it's sunny or whether it's
cloudy
it'll be consistent whether you're
feeling like things are going good or
you feel like things are not going good
my peace I leave with you in mark
chapter six verse three through six you
need to see this mark chapter 6 verses
three through six Jesus is once again
tested and notice these verses is not
this the carpenter the son of Mary and
brother of James so uh go to the next
verse please I want to get to go to that
oh yeah right here but jesus said to
them a prophet is not without honor
except in his own Watts country among
his own relatives and in his own house
verse five now he could do no mighty
work there except that he laid his hands
on a few sick people and healed them and
that's a question why could Jesus not do
any mighty works in this place
because they did not watch they did not
believe in him they rejected the Messiah
can you imagine what it how many of you
know what it feel like to feel rejection
you know what that's like you know how
our feelings can get when we get when we
sense that we're being rejected now I
want you to imagine Jesus he is the king
of heaven and he comes to earth and he
cannot even do many mighty works because
the people they are like yeah
were not interested did Jesus keep his
peace even in rejection jesus said the
peace I leave for you is a piece that is
rejection proof it's been rejection
tried so whether you're going through
good times or bad times whether the Sun
is out or it's not whether whether or
you are being rejected or not my peace
that I leave with you is a piece that
has wasted all of these issues but of it
even in the Garden of Gethsemane you
remember Jesus said my soul is exceeding
what sorrowful even unto death and Jesus
goes into the garden and he prays let me
ask you did Jesus keep his peace in the
garden come with me
Matthew 26 Matthew 26 you see beloved
Jesus's peace is a sorrow tested peace
that's the kind of peace that you and I
need notice what from Matthew 26 verse
61 to 63 Jesus is now in the midst of
persecution he is about to be nailed to
the cross and notice what it says here
they said this fellow said I am able to
destroy the temple of God and build it
in three days
verse 62 and the high priests arose and
said to him do you answer nothing what
is it these men testify against you
verse 63 man I knew it
alright so the King the new king same
version says but Jesus kept his silence
I like the way the KJV puts it because
it says Jesus held his
what did he hold his peace how many of
you know what it's like to hold your
peace and not let go of it even when
you're in the midst of persecution but
love it this is what Jesus is offering
us he says this is the kind of peace
that I leave for you my peace I leave
with you if you allow me to rule in your
heart I will give you this peace why
because I am the king of peace and I
have proven it so find the king of peace
if Jesus is your king then what should
be reigning in your heart why because
he's a king of what he's a king of peace
so Jesus says listen I'm leaving you my
peace and the evidence that I am your
king is that you live under peace do you
know the Bible says no you're not that
to whom ye yield yourselves servants to
obey his servants you are to whom you
obey so if you're obeying Jesus what do
you have I mean let me just let me try
that again
if you are obeying Jesus if Jesus is
your king and you obey Him
what do you have in your heart even when
it's stormy even when the clouds are out
even when your friends turn on you even
when your husband gets you mad
even even when your wife gets you mad
hold your peace everybody say with me
hold your peace but that was Satan's
trying to take your peace he's trying to
take your peace he's trying to get you
caught up in these nine kings of
emotional stress he's trying to get you
so that you let go of your peace and
when you let go of your peace beloved
you're letting go of Jesus first Samuel
15:23 says this for rebellion is as the
sin of witchcraft let me read that again
rebellion is as the sin of witchcraft
let me ask you a question
how can you rebel against the Prince of
Peace what does it mean to rebel against
the Prince of Peace it means to rebel
against peace
that's not so Redell against the king of
peace means that you're rebelling
against the principle of peace so what
does it mean to rebel against the
principle of peace it means to be under
the Dominion of stress anxiety fear
depression discard that's what it means
now the Bible says rebellion is as the
sin of witchcraft beloved listen to me
reject the devil's attempt to cast his
spells of depression anxiety fear stress
doubt hatred reject those spells because
that's what they are they are spells of
the enemy designed to take us out of the
arms of the Prince of Peace it is the
enemy's sorceress attempt to lead you to
doubt the power of God to deliver you
how many of you have ever been subject
to sorcery Wow but I need you to
understand that God is calling us to
something much greater he's calling us
to something much more powerful and I
want to close with this I know I'm
saying I'm gonna close with this and I
know you're gonna when you see this
you're gonna be like oh don't worry you
give me five minutes and I will be done
but you have to see this do you want to
go your way or God's Way because God's
Way lead you to God your way lead you to
Sodom yes
so if I know then that if I choose my
way I'm gonna end up in trouble I'm
gonna end up under the Dominion of these
kings these emotional Kings then I know
that I should choose God's way so my
question is where is God's Way in the
where in the where in the where if God's
ways in a sanctuary that then the
sanctuary might contain the very
principles I need to help me overcome my
issues of stress so we're going to do
this very very quickly listen you know
these six articles of furniture the
altar of sacrifice
there's the Laver there's a table of
showbread there's the altar of incense
there's a candlestick and there's the
Ark of the Covenant
Ark of the Covenant brick
say this very simply to you guys listen
the other sacrifice what was about the
principle of self-sacrifice of
sacrificing things and I want to say to
you simply that we have to learn how to
sacrifice stress we have to learn how to
lay stress on the
funny negative stress is called distress
but there's a thing called positive
stress did you know that positive stress
is it's called you stress EU stress you
stress them that the phrase EU it means
good-good stress so how many of you
remember when you were getting married
were you stressed how many of you
remember when you are getting married
now I know why you're saying no because
you you are not distressed you were not
distressed but were you stressed what
kind of stress wasn't good stress oh man
I've got all these things all these
things we got a plan and on stress but
it's a good stress do you know that good
stress is actually healthy for you good
stress listen to me you stress look at
you stress is the type of stress that
athletes have when they're on the field
and there there's 20 seconds left in the
game or 15 seconds and they look at the
situation and there's an excitement
because okay everything is on the line
they're not like oh I'm the stress when
they're like you stress like come on
guys we got to do this they take a
negative situation but they have a
positive outlook on it and beloved this
is what Jesus had the reason he was able
to defeat stress is because he knew his
mission he knew his purpose and even
when time was running out he was
experiencing not distress but you stress
I've got a mission to accomplish and I
will not fail nor be discouraged so
we've got to learn how to replace
distress with you stress slay distress
and replace it but you stress I want to
share with you something most very
quickly because there's something called
catastrophizing anyone ever heard of
that yeah
yeah catastrophizing
it is the utter panic that you
experience because you dropped your pen
on the ground when you should have had
it in your hand someone stepped on my
shoe look at this what am I going to do
now that's cut how many of you how many
of you are good catastrophize you won't
let me tell you something this is
serious
listen listen guys in Daniel chapter
seven and eight there's a power called a
little horn we know it's a satanic power
but the Bible says the lift of this
little horn that he magnified himself
the nasty something what is Satan's job
he magnifies he makes things appear
bigger than they really are but ever we
have to learn how to slay stress we have
to learn how to de magnify the situation
what's gonna happen now we
you are sitting in my favorite seat I am
about to have a bad day in church today
we gotta stop that let's go to the labor
very quickly the labor is about washing
away stuff isn't it the labor is about
Christ coming to wash away our debts now
how do you get into debt how do you get
in the debt when you when you borrow you
get into debt is that right when you
borrow you get into debt your nominees
are in debt to worry because we borrow
trouble yeah we gotta stop borrowing
trouble guys we gotta learn how to wash
away that debt don't look look I'm the
Bible says sufficient is the problems
for today don't think about tomorrow
we gotta learn how to wash that away
what about the table of showbread the
table of showbread was about the Word of
God but the Bible says that listen we
should talk to ourselves in hymns and
and sounds anyone ever heard of
self-talk you know we talked so much in
ourselves man you're not good you're not
worth anything and here's a crazy thing
is most of the self-talk we do we don't
even hear it
so we're going out day by day talking
this negative self-talk God says this
and I want you to talk the Word of God I
want you to concentrate on the Word of
God I want you to talk positively not
negatively what about the candlestick
many of us love dwelling on the dark
side all we see is the darkness God says
you are the light of the world you need
to start having a positive outlook and
not a negative one
God says listen I need you to be that
light I need you to start talking to
yourself with my words not your own
self-doubt and all those things I need
you to wash away that that debt wash
away that sorrow don't borrow that sore
it's not yours why did you take it upon
yourself I came to take it from you
why have you taken it upon yourself your
against me right now you're rebelling
against me by taking that worry upon
yourself the altar of incense we got to
learn how to keep our mind focused on
heavenly things we got to learn how to
keep our mind stayed on Christ and
finally beloved the Ark of the Covenant
the Bible tells us great peace great
peace how they that love thy law beloved
listen to me if you would just consider
God's Way it is the secret it is the
secret
to slaying your stress
[Music]
but of it it's stress while many of us
can't even worship God right we come to
church stress we leave Church stressed
we allow the sermon to stress us we
allow the pastor to stress us we just we
are stressed lovers do you know that
stress can release you can dude do you
realize that you can become addicted to
stress physiologically that it releases
stuff in your body that you get to the
point where you are you have become so
used to stress that you dwell on it you
actually begin to boast about your
stress beloved it's time to flay
distress
it's time to worship the king of peace
and he's not I'm not saying you know
you're not gonna have tried in life I'm
not saying your situations are hard
you're making a big deal out that's not
I'm not trying to minimize what we may
be going through I'm going through stuff
guys I want you to know like it's a real
battle so trust me I'm not trying to
minimize anything do you know I were to
stab the other day that over 85% of
pastors that that people that are
pastors quit pastoring in the first six
years because they cannot handle the
stress or the abuse that they sometimes
get yet there is such a thing as
pastoral abuse it is real
but beloved God doesn't look at me and
say well I understand your stress so you
can go ahead and just be stressed out
neither did he say that to you whatever
stress is you're going through God says
I need you I need you to submit to the
king of peace stop borrowing stuff that
doesn't belong to you that's not yours
and that's not but Lord is my problem no
it's not yours I bought that for you on
the cross I bought that from you on the
cross so I'm gonna ask as I'm Darren
please Darren's gonna come and lead us
in prayer and I'm gonna ask I'm gonna
make a simple appeal
raise your hand if you have been a slave
to stress be honest just be honest don't
put on that you know I am holy look on
your face right now be honest if you
haven't then praise God but if you have
been a slave to stress you have you have
suffered at the hand of these nine kings
of emotional stress and you're saying
Lord no more no more I'm gonna submit
I'm gonna give these to you and it is my
desire to live under the king of peace
that's your desire we want you to raise
your hands the Lord sees your hands I
want to invite you to kneel as Darren
leads us Emperor
and your Heavenly Father we come to you
the Sabbath but you left our hearts to
you we thank you Lord for giving us this
day that we can commercial I asked you
to take anything in our lives that is
separating us from you at this the
stress of life the cares of life more
than getting away their weekend
that steals our piece from his Lord I
hope I ask you to in a special way bless
each one of us here today in the Lord as
we come in worship you and helped us to
have a blessed day
the rest of this afternoon in Christ
amen we'll invite you all to stand as we
sing our closing song
[Music]
you